Hello.
Welcome back.
In this lesson, we are going to see how to develop a USP H.I.G. keyboard using our Cuber mixing cube
idea.
So I'm going to create a new project.
I'll click over here.
You project or select my port over here.
SDM 32, a four one one.
And then also like this.
We start off by clearing open out.
Click over here, clip in, out, I'll say yes.
Over here.
I've said it to, oh, gee, by coming over here, multimedia, um, actually connectivity, USP, LTG
mode.
It's a device only.
Now we've got to set a clock.
I'll go to the UN system, call RACC, and then high speed Klok, which is HSC or select Christo's large
ceramic resonator.
This is based on the setting of my board.
I'm using the SDM 32 F for one one for each board.
Okay, next we've got to go to middleware and it's like the class.
I'll come to Mido Middleware over here.
And then you s.b device class for FSD IP.
We want to do an HIV device, human interface device.
Okay, so now this is the arm does well, although we've done it similar to what we did when creating
the HIV mouse.
But to create a keyboard we have to do exactly the same thing and then change the P I.D. number so that
our computer will identify what microcontroller is a keyboard.
Well, by here I'm going to change the PDA from two to three.
One, five, two, two, two, three, one, six.
So I click over here and change the five to six.
Okay.
I'm also going to initialize our push button so that we can use it in our experiment.
To be a zero is where the push button is connected to on my or my disco board.
Where is P is you.
I've got P three over here.
This is P is.
You said it to GPL.
Your input.
Like this?
No, we can go to the clock conflagration tub and you can see we've selected the HSC here, the highspeed
external, and then it's set to ninety six megahertz, which is quite high.
I'll leave this the way it is now or generate the project by coming to project manager over.
I'll give the project to name.
I call this USP underscore.
H.I.G. underscore.
Keyboard.
And then I'm going to select my two chain SDM 32 to IDC and then I'll click generate over here.
So this a project, this, I mean, see fall, and then, um, as we saw in the setup, we did exactly
what we did for the, um, for the most project.
So the way this is going to act as a keyboard will be through some manual changes that would do to the
code.
Here we start off by changing the report cites the report, the end and point report.
Size is different for the mouse and the, um, and the keyboard.
So we go to a USP device, H.I.G. dot each file to change the to locate the USB device, H.I.G. dot
h file.
You click on middleware you USP device library class H.I.G. include which is I n c and then you find
the fallen open.
So like we said, the default, if you um if you set us up in Cuba makes that default is setup for mouse.
So we've got to change it to give us the keyboard.
Right.
OK.
So this is where it gives us the the end point size, which is two x zero four here.
I'll put a comment.
I'll see.
Change to zero x zero eight four keyboard.
So this is going to be the first change we are.
We apply to I'll just change this four to eight.
OK.
Next, we have to change the interface protocol to keyboard.
Now, we can do that in the implementation file of this same file.
This is the head of our USP device on a score, HIIT dots each.
We've got to go to the DOT, see Falin perform this change.
I'll come to source over here.
USP device on this score.
H.I.G. dot h.
And then I'll scroll down.
We've got to locate the descriptor.
Should be down here somewhere.
We are looking for this over here.
USP, H.I.G. Configuration, FSD Descriptor.
Remember, we are using a word device in FSM mode, not an H.S. mode.
If we were using an HST mode will come to HST descriptor.
Which has configuration descriptor.
But because we've set it up for effort, we'll come over here.
What we're looking for is to change the, um, the protocol from mouse to keyboard.
And there are comments here describing what each line over here does.
When you come down over here to line number one hundred and sixty one interface protocol.
Zero is none.
One is keyboard.
Two is mouse currently by default.
It is said to two.
I'm going to change this to one for keyboard like we are told to do over here.
Now we've got a we've got to change the, um, the, uh, the.
Report descriptor.
We've changed.
Thus far, the configuration descriptor known as another one known as the.
The report descriptor.
This is war tells the, um, the computer.
This is a mouse.
When you receive this.
This is a click.
This is, um.
This is right click left click scroll wheel, et cetera.
We've got to change it for keyboard.
Um, so we've got to locate it first.
So this was the March report Descriptor, HIIT, Mones Report Descriptor.
This information here encapsulates what the it means to be a mouse.
It encapsulates the essence of a mouse.
So this shows what this computer is able to know.
This is a mouse and how it should sort of translate to information.
So for a keyboard, there is a different set of numbers that you need to use.
This can be generated from the, uh, the USP Web site.
And you can also get it from S.T. to people at SD Microelectronics.
Um, so I have this file here which has that descriptor for USP, um, for keyboard.
This over here gives us the same, the same um, the same thing for keyboard.
So I'm gonna copy everything here.
Control a and then control.
See I'm going to touch this to the lesson as well and I'm going to paste this here.
Right.
So once I've pasted this here, we can delete the first one.
We can delete the first one.
You note that this one is still called H.I.G. March Descriptor.
We can change the name to keyboard if we want, but because we have two of them now, we can delete
the one for the amount.
We don't need most in this project.
So I just delete this from here like this.
Either that or we could have used an if else and just set the mouse to zero.
We can see if zero execute the mouse else execute this other block.
But this is easier.
Okay, so this one over here is the arm.
The report descriptor for keyboard.
Okay.
No, no, we've changed the reports descriptor from most a keyboard.
We've got to change the size.
When we come to the dot each fall, the size, the report descriptive size is defined.
We've got to change it over here.
It set us seventy four.
We we have to change the size because as you saw, the array is bigger than this one here.
It's bigger than the one we deleted from Mount.
We have to change this to one eighty seven and um we can um we can rename this too keyboard or if we
don't want to make a lot of changes we can still keep the same name.
I can see why he has to assess H.I.G. Mount report this group to size.
We could have just created a new defined statement and call it H I.D. keyboard report scripter aside
and find every word that this is used and then replace it with keyboard.
But an easier way is just to change this.
Yeah.
No, we can go to our main would see fall and then um and then run the experiment.
Basically when we um when we press our push button we want to press a particular keyboard key such that
our push-button will be detected as a key by our computer.
When I come to mean that C over here and in our infinite loop, we'll check without a push button is
pressed.
We just see if on a score cheapie I owe on the score we'd read a pin and then the pin Portas gpa you
it penis cheapie I o on the school pin on the scores.
You read it.
This is Piers Zero.
If this is set up we checked out by saying GPA you on the school pin on this course set.
If such is the state then.
We want to do something and there's something we want to do is send a key press, a key basic, just
like we did in the mouse example we need to do over here.
Well, we need to declare a buffer.
We'll see say this time the buffer size is eight.
I'll see you in eight.
On this score, t in key buffer.
Oh, I see.
Buffer.
And the size is eight like this.
Okay, so let's input our data.
Um, so we have eight eight spaces.
That's the size of our buffer, just like we did for the mouse.
I'll come over here.
Index zero is for the report.
Idee Index zero here.
Reports I.D..
Just pass one.
And then index one is the modifier.
Above zero.
Indexed to his T or E m.
Index three.
This key code data.
Actual data that we wish to send.
Index four, five, six and seven, equal key data.
I'm going to set all of these two zero initially.
This is for certain.
Two zero two zero.
This is five.
There's a six set index, six two zero.
Oh, set index seven to zero as well.
Is six, seven.
Okay, so we can send a key.
We can send Paige down, press the, um, the hexadecimal code for the ISO X for E.
So to do that, we just place it in the key code data.
But I'm going to place it at is index over here.
So I would say if I were a push button is pressed, then I want to see what keys Buffa Index three equals
through X.
Through X for E.
This is on page down press.
And once we've done this, once we've seen Saturdays, we've got to use the, um, the H.I.G. send reports
to send a buffer, the top of our content, just like we did for the mouse so we can come over here.
The defense argument is the, um, the handle the USB device handle.
The second argument is the buffer and then the buffer size.
And we know we find a handle in the, um, the device does see fall.
They use device to see.
So I'm going to come to source over here, USP device to see.
And then over here, we should have this.
I'm going to copy this and I'm going to declare it.
And it may not see us external.
Put it up here.
I'll put the extend key word here like this so we can call our function now the send report function.
I'm going to copy this controversy to copy, because we need this for the first document of our function.
And I'll say.
The function is USP D on the school, each I.D. on the school send report.
The first argument is the, um, the address of the Hando.
Then the, um, the report Buffa keeps both over here and the size, which is eight like this.
So what we have to do is to, um, press and release.
We know when you are using the keyboard on the computer.
If you press a key, nothing happens.
You have to press and release it, press it.
Did, uh, a press or a key is read when it's pressed and released.
You can realize that if you would just drop your hand.
You know, dependent on the keyboard, some keys.
You have to quickly, you know, press and lift your hand.
Others, if you keep your hand on it, you might press more.
But in our case, we are doing the press and release over here.
Um, so once we've done this, we would apply a bit of delay and then we release or C on underscore
delay fifty.
Yeah.
Like this.
And then I'll send a release or simply copy this.
The um copy this from here.
Over here.
Paste it over here like this to release me.
Basically send no data so I'll pass it over here like this.
Okay.
Remember, when you press the page down on your keyboard, it screws the arm.
It's close the screen.
It will give you a dance crew.
Right.
So that's the effect we expect to see.
And, um, I'm going to build.
Let's see.
I'm gonna include USP, H.I.G. device, the H over here.
So I wouldn't get any arrows.
Also include U.
S bd underscore HIIT dot h.
Like this.
Okay.
Click over here to build.
It's pulled successfully.
I'm gonna download onto my board by clicking debug.
Selectees.
They don't say, okay, over here.
Right.
Okay, so just exit this since it's downloaded, the download verified so slick successfully so I can
exit this and test it out without being in that book for you.
So this is our USP keyboard project of downloaded onto the board of Built downloaded onto the board
by going through the, um, the debug sequence over here.
I'm trying on a different computer because my computer for record in the video.
Um, the fast USB port is being used for an external hard disk.
So I'm testing on a different computer.
So you can see that the IDC looks, uh, a bit different.
And over here we have just the USP, the the HIIT keyboard, uh, project.
So.
Okay.
This is our project.
And then we said we're doing page down.
Page down.
Is similar to pressing that down RACQ on your keyboard.
So what I'm gonna do is I'm gonna press the button cause we expect this to scroll down the page.
If it's working.
When I press the blue button on all this keyboard.
So as I press the page jumps.
And now we at the end.
I'll go up and impress again when I press.
It just jumps.
It goes.
So this page down.
So this how we build the HIIT keyboard.
If you have any issues with the setup or you face any problems, just leave in the Q&A section.
I'll see you later.